hey everyone welcome to another lesson
in the stsa automation course today we
are going to learn about how you can
Generate random values and enter into
your test steps in
tosa now we have already seen how you
can enter input values into your test
cases but these are all uh fixed values
which you are entering right static data
but what if you want to make your test
more Dynamic right so every time you run
there is a different value you are
entering into the test
case
right and that is where tosa provides
you a way to Generate random values be
it a integer a number or a string right
so let's see what are the different ways
of generating random values for your
test cases in
tosa so the first way is uh generating
the random integer values right so these
are random numbers which can be
generated by tosa and you can enter
these numbers uh in any field which
accepts some numerical data okay now
there are two ways of doing it one is
generate an integer Without Limits right
so here you can use an expression like
this so we are going to see how and
where you'll be using that right so you
have to use R&D and then uh in square
brackets you have to enter the length of
random number number right so that could
be either 10 9 or 50 100 whatever you
want to have the length of your number
right so this will generate a random
number of that particular length which
is defined by you okay the other way of
doing it is generating a integer within
a certain range right so if you want to
generate a number between a th000 or and
a 10,000 right
then you have to define the expression
like R&D then you have to define the
lower limit and then the upper limit so
what tosa will do it will generate a
random number between this lower limit
and upper limit okay so this is the
range between which these numbers will
be
generated so these are the two ways of
generating random numbers in tosa and
then you can also generate numbers with
decimal places okay
so here you have to define the number
length and the expression would be R&D
decimal and in square brackets you have
to put the length of random number okay
so what would be the length of random
number and then you have to also mention
the decimal places so what number of
decimal places you want your number to
be right so it could be two it could be
three it could be four or any particular
decimal places so tosa is going to
generate a number with that number of
decimal
places next you can also
generate a number with decimal places
within a certain range okay so you have
to uh follow this expression R&D decimal
here you need to mention the decimal
places and then the lower limit and
upper limit okay so tosa is going to
generate a number with certain decimal
places between between a certain range
okay so that's how you can generate a
random number with
decimals now the next thing uh is the
random strings so this random string
could be a mix of random numbers and
letters and this will be generated by
tosa okay so you can generate a random
string uh the expression is random text
and in square bracket you need to define
the desired string length and it will
going to generate the random text with
this particular length
Okay so these are all the ways how you
can generate different numbers number
with decimals or uh strings right so
there are couple of other options as
well like you can generate um a string
with a
timestamp right but um these are
generally used in your test cases okay
so now now let's see how this could be
useful in a scenario where you can
generate this random data and then
insert it into your test
case so I'm in my workspace in tosa
Commander where I'm going to add another
scenario where we could use the random
values right uh provided by tosa so
let's see we are going to pick up a
application with a particular scenario
so this would be our application which
is a register page right so here the
user can come in and register its
account in this particular application
right so he has to enter the first name
last name email telephone password
confirm password and then some um
options which he needs to select and
then click on continue to register an
account on this particular application
okay so we are going to automate this
using tosa and we'll see how and where
we can use the random value generation
feature provided by
tosa so first of all uh let's go ahead
and uh create a new test case folder
right for our application I'm going to
call
it
tutorial
ninja that's the application name so
I'll keep it that
okay and then here we need to again
um create our test cases or we can
create some other subfolders but for now
let's create our test cases okay so the
first test case right uh would be for a
registering and application right or we
have to first open the application as
well which is a prerequisite so let's do
that okay so this is my first test case
open application and then I can add
another test case is and I will say
register
account okay and this is my second test
case now for open application I need
some test steps and for that I can use
some default module right the same way
we have used it in our other application
okay now in order to uh get a standard
module right uh
one way is you can go and search it in
your standard modules right or the other
way around is just go to your test case
and press contrl T right so when you
press control T it will open a window
where all the different modules present
in this workspace will be displayed and
here you can search your module which
you want to include in your test case or
test steps right
now I need something called open URL
okay
so this is the open URL module
right and this will allow me to open an
application on the browser right so
let's grab the URL
here and I'll put the value as it is in
the value right the action mode would be
input the data type is still string
right so that open a URL in a specific
browser now coming to our this
particular application we also need a
test configuration parameter right so
let's go ahead and add it we can add it
from here uh from the test case folder
right so go here and you will see test
create test configuration parameter we
have already seen this so we'll select
browser and in the browser
Chrome browser so that the application
opens in this particular browser okay so
the initial steps are now done and let's
go to register account where we will
again create a module for our
registration page right let's create a
new module here right so let's first
create a new module folder so right
click and select create folder here I'm
going to enter some name right it could
be any anything but I would just enter
the application name
here okay now we need to add different
modules for this application and the
best way to do it is directly scan the
application right the page which you are
trying to automate so right click and go
to scan
application there we have to select our
application which we want to scan okay
so I'll go to this and click on scan
now it will ask me to click on controls
in my application to basically add those
controls right so let me click on first
name last name email telephone password
the confirm password the Subscribe
button the privacy policy checkbox and
the continue
button okay so all of these controls I
want to add into my module
okay so click on Save and click on
close so that is basically going to add
all the controls in this particular
module which is register
account okay now what we want to do is
let's drag it here so that we can see
both the test cases and modules right
and I want to add this module right so
either you can again press contr T and
search for this or you can directly drag
and drop into this particular test step
okay so this will add this module and
all the controls into this particular
test case as different test steps
okay and as you can see it has got
different controls and we have to enter
different values right now the
straightforward V which we have already
seen is to directly enter different
values into these fields right and it
would work as usual so I can enter a
name first name last name email
telephone password right but then uh we
are trying to learn how we can Generate
random values for Strings or numbers in
tosa okay so that uh we can make our
test case more Dynamic
okay so um let's see how we can generate
the random string okay so you need to
follow the expression here in the value
you need to type this curly braces and
then you need to type
random okay and it would be popped up
you will see random text so either you
type it or select it from the options
and then square bracket okay and you
need to enter some length here so let me
enter
five okay and close the curly braces
that's it
when you press enter you will see uh
this
highlighted uh value which is random
text and the length is five okay
similarly I can do it for last name so
I'll say
random
right
text and in square bracket again five
okay and press enter so you can see both
of these values are now random values
which which will be generated by
tosa now if you want to verify what tosa
is actually doing for these values right
whether it is generating random values
or not that also you can do so go here
right click and then there is an option
called translate value okay so click on
that and you should see a translation
right for this particular expression so
it will show you the value which it is
printing or it is generating
and using it for this particular field
okay uh it's some random value um as we
have put random text right so it's a
combination of um text and numbers okay
so it is generating this particular
value now similarly for this you can
also translate the value and it will
show you a random value
okay
so let's enter some um value in this
email field okay so test at
um
test at qscript
tocom this is my email right uh in
telephone let's see how we can use the
random number okay so how you can
generate a random number and put it in
this telephone Field so for
that again um start with C braces and
then type R&D okay so that's the
expression for random number after this
either you can um do a range right or
you can directly put the number of
digits you want okay so the digits
number of digits for telone is generally
10 so I'll keep it as 10 and then hit
enter and you will see the expression is
converted right again if you want to see
what is the value just click on
translate value
and you will see some random number
being
generated
okay now password I will put some
password here
okay and here as well the confirm
password now later I will show you also
how you can Generate random passwords
right and you can also use it in confirm
password but for that we need to use a
different concept right so I'll take it
up in some of the future sessions
now for this radio button we have to
click on it
right and checkbox we need to select
true or
false and then we need to click on the
okay button right so these are all the
values or all the actions which we want
to perform on all these different
controls um so now let's go ahead and
let's see if we are able to see all the
random values which we have generated
are being entered into the application
when we'll run this particular
application
okay so let's go ahead and close this
existing
browser and let's run this from our test
case folder okay so go to run in
scratchbook and it should open a browser
with the
application and it will enter all the
values okay
so as you can see it has entered some
random uh values for first name for last
name and for telephone right so these
are the random numbers and random
strings which we have generated are
being entered into these fields
right now there is some failure
currently right and uh that's because it
is not able to click on a particular
control right and the thing it is
complaining is there is more than one
control found for action one
okay so we know the problem is with the
radio button right so there are more
than one control with the same
properties now obviously um the way to
fix this is to select some other
property value right but this is part of
our module right um and we need to
actually rescan the module and we need
to change this particular property value
for this control right so that's the
solution for this kind of issues which
will come across every application right
so there could be some common controls
which have some same values and these
are not uh uniquely identified by tosa
right so in that you need to intervene
and you need to change that control
property value now I'm going to take
this up in the next session where I will
show you how you can rescan your module
right um from the application and pull
the different values or change the
values or properties of a particular
control which are not unique okay so
we'll see this in our next session